[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right uh welcome to the stoa
where we i don't have it in front of me
where we dialogue
at the nice edge of the present moment
uh you know the drill yeah i got like a
c on that peter
i'll work on it um very excited to be
back with bonita
uh good to see familiar faces uh looks
like 40 people in the call right now
um for those who are new welcome uh
i'll just go over this structure really
quickly this is part of a
four-week series called the hollow and
this is week two
and it's going to consist of a
presentation
by bonita and followed by a q a
there's a lot of content i'll let benita
speak more to that
but we have we have limited time and
we're going to make
uh best use of it with those components
um i'm going to post in the chat
the uh links to the slides
from last week and then slides for this
week
is part two so that's in the chat right
now for any of you who are interested
and with that over to you bonita
oh yes okay hi everyone
um yeah nice to see you here uh just a
couple of comments
um you know we had a question last time
about
um more participation
and um you know one of the things that
we're trying to do here
in the stoa when in any kind of kind of
artistic or aesthetic artifact is we
compress
time so the presentation i'm showing you
took me about
i don't know 80 hours 90 hours 100 hours
to do not to mention
the preamble the work itself the
conceptual work
and then we compress it down so that you
can experience some of it within
four short sessions um each one of these
sessions obviously could
support and anchor workshops we could
workshop this so
each session could be six hour workshop
um but that's uh you know that's a big
ask
um i i don't have the time to volunteer
that kind of
uh service um to the stoa so
what i want to invite you to do is is
experience these get a hit off of
what is happening here perhaps
hang out with your friends watch the
videos again
we make the slides available to you
their animated slides
you can experience them over and over
again and set up groups to
have conversations around some of this
stuff because these are just
provocations of what you might be
talking about or thinking about
or insights that you could have and
those could be you know happen help
elsewhere so we really want to encourage
um
you to take advantage of the material
itself and bring it into community
and bring it into a larger conversation
so
um yeah so if you
if some of you are here and you didn't
either
uh watch the video from last time or
weren't here last time unfortunately you
might be
quite lost because in the sense making
series
they build on each other right so um a
lot was covered
in the in the first session it doesn't
mean you can't enjoy what's coming
but it doesn't really stand on its own
if you're in this position come to it
with a much more imaginary
orientation and with that
i think we shall begin
where am i
oops
okay so this is part two of the hollow
the hollow is a place where we come to
talk about secret things perhaps things
that are just on the
tips of our imagination we also we must
remember
that this is designed as dispatches from
a time in between worlds
they're just little vignettes of what
we're trying to deal with they're
half-born thoughts
so each slide kind of rhymes with the
other slide but it
doesn't build itself conceptually after
we do the presentation
then we'll get into some of the
conceptual territory according to
uh where you want to go with your
questions or we could just augment it
into more imaginaries
all right so we are going to
look at three metaphysical primes of
modernity
um time change and causality so um
today we're going to look specifically
at time
and why we're looking at these
is because they capture our ability
to think about reality to think about
our challenges to think about who we
are they reduce our imagination
to the forms of time change and
causality
that modernity offers so we want to try
to look at these from a different place
so in these presentations we'll all
we'll look at
what modernity offers and then we'll
look at some
alternatives but there are only one
alternative or two alternatives the
the real exercises here is can you get
insights into a whole different
relationship
to time than what modernity offers and
can you
start practicing not falling into
the limited mental models of time
change and causality of modernity so we
will be presenting some alternatives
but they're not the only alternatives um
so just be aware of that
all right so um in
uh gesture talked a lot about this that
the
mythic structure of consciousness time
was cyclical
um and um focused on the past
in the mental structure of consciousness
in modernity
we spatialize time so we have things
like the timeline
you know we order events along the
timeline
and even in this complex
phase diagram of time you see
there's a separation they're the few the
the
the futures in the top half of the
expansion the passes in the bottom half
and this is a wormhole here that
supposedly
you can time travel between them but
there's a gap so it's still this
spatialization of time where there's a
gap between the past and the present
and in a sense there's a sense of ever
widening gap
so even in our sophisticated models of
time
they're spatialized and they have this
sense of
gap berkson said time
is an invention or is nothing at all
which opened up the way for example
we're going to look at whitehead to
imagine
or reinvent what um taught our
relationship to time
so one of the things about making a
timeline what we do in modernity
which is um quite um impressive
really is so this is a gift of modernity
is we get to have these wonderful maps
about for example the
um the evolution of the universe
so just take a moment and look at what
we
have discerned about
our universe from 13
galactic ages ago and this will go
all the way from the present from the
past to the present and then
speculate into the future so we have
this
timeline it ticks away
one of the things to notice is that it
starts with geological processes
and then starts to move into geo and
biological processes so
there's a continuity here between the
geologic and the biologic
so this is a very modern way to think of
what's what's been going on
and just let yourself enter this deep
time
and instead of thinking of this as the
universe
everything that's exists today
this is also our past this is your past
this is how long it takes for you to get
here
all these extraordinary events are
compressed
into the person called you
[Music]
so what does it take to be a u
includes all of this
all of these contingencies all of these
miracles
were necessary the necessary
parts of your genealogy
even these extinction events were
necessary for you to be here
and you see extinctions events of 75
species go extinct another 75
of species extinctions
whales return to the water
so
we go into the future
the oil reserves are replenished
[Music]
so
earth oceans evaporate mars approaches
the habitable zone
okay
so one of the mistakes we make as
moderns when we look at a timeline like
this
is we see the events in the past is
somehow
completed we see the events in the
present is somehow
just shown up and
another way to look at this is is that
everything that exists now
is just more of what has been happening
all along you didn't all of a sudden
show up
you're not possible without all these
other aspects
of evolution and cosmology also
happening
they didn't happen in the past the stars
are still burning the sun is still
um living out its lifespan the earth is
still moving the plates are still moving
the climate is still changing
all of this preamble to you
is also present today
it's all simultaneously dynamic
so the timeline is really cool because
it gives us this understanding of these
events but it makes it seem like
something's
done and over with but the geology is
done and now it's
life and the animals are done and now
everything of importance happens on our
branch of the tree
but there's no such thing as our branch
of the tree
it's always the whole that is evolving
at the same time
and this is a modern aboriginal
painting of time and the big difference
here
so this is represents you could say it's
not this literal but
this represents the past this represents
the future you notice the placement
the futures in the ground emerging like
a
seed not in the sky up there
and the difference here is that the
individual
is not suspended between the past and
the future
but anchored by the past and the future
that the past and futures implicate in
the position that the
that the individual holds right now
that's a big difference
right between being suspended
the past is gone the future has not yet
come
versus everything that's been before and
everything that's coming
composes me in the presence now
it anchors me in where i am
do you see that can you feel the
difference between that
so it's not like they don't have a sense
of past and present and future
but they're not they're on this timeline
where there are gaps and then we're
suspended in the middle and
part of the reasons why we can even have
a meme like a time between worlds is
because of the way we
arrange time and that we're always
in this sense we'll always be half born
right we're always between becoming
and emerging and having been and not yet
and this is actually psychologically
quite unhealthy
because we never quite leave and we
never quite get there
there's a sense of suspension and not a
sense of belonging
and even the future as it orients itself
is implicit in where we are right now
so this notion of this this kind of
living
wholeness between
quote unquote the events of the past
that which
is actually doesn't make sense and the
events
of the future so
um this is like i said it's a modern
indigenous
painting but you can really see the
difference between
being suspended in time versus being
anchored
by time by the profound simultaneity
of the dynamic processes of evolution
or and cosmogenesis
we have those two terms cosmogenesis and
evolution because we also make a gap
between
la you know living and non-living so all
these all these categories we have
create gaps
another way to look at it the way the
greeks uh the greeks
thoughts uh there was something
something funny about time
and you can see you can feel how this
still leads to modernity
they had three words uh for a time
uh most people know the first two cronus
is the
passage of time um
and it's represented here in these
depictions
as kind of a burden the tree is old
it's been burdened by time all these
these
kind of uh time burdens
then there was cairo's and kairos is
a has the quality of being
saturated with resonance so it's a sense
of being playful or opportune time
um but there's still something you know
there's still um
there's still this kind of specter of
death here
um and so that's a depiction by this
artist of cairo's
then there's a third meaning of time
that is
called chinos and
kainos um is a word that i learned from
donna haraway
and she translates it as now a time of
beginnings a time for
ongoing so she says nothing in kindness
must mean conventional past presence or
future
it's full of inheritance remembering
comings nurturing
and so this notion of this this being
composed by and anchored in
time versus um
versus being suspended between time so
there's a progression here
in this way of relating through through
time
now gepser said that um
the new structure of consciousness would
have this quality of time
freedom so this is i think the
progression of these
this artist's work is this one is much
more uh
yeah like she's becoming liberated from
uh time itself and
gabster said that time freedom is
is being aware of time as an activity of
consciousness
and this gives us a lot of wiggle room
so if my consciousness
is constructing time and then i live
inside that
construct then i can actively
and creatively re-imagine a relationship
to time
and so gebzer said that that it's the
point is not to get
rid of any concept of time is to
is to take control and be creatively and
imaginative
about how we relate to time and and
and be able that to be a lens by which
we
we reveal more of reality
we reveal more of the universe we reveal
more about our
our own place in the universe instead of
being stuck in one time construction
so one person who reimagined
time was uh whitehead
and one of the interesting things is
there's a lot
of resonance rhythm rhyming between
whitehead
and indigenous conceptions metaphysics
and that it's not coincidental not
because white had studied
indigenous people because he moved back
toward process
thinking pure process thinking and the
interesting thing about whitehead
is one of his his critiques about
time as understood by modernity
is he said in modernity in this in this
scientific materialism this mentalist
attitude we have
we only include actuals we only include
the actual events
not the potentials so he said this is so
we put the actual events in the past the
potentials in the future and he said
this
is a um incorrect categorization
that every moment actuals and potentials
exist together
and the potentials even though they're
not made actuals
they subsist and they're causally
effective
in the present moment in other words
he's saying what the future is is the
causally effective potentials
that exist in the present and that's how
we imagine
that there is a future calling us not
because we can get ahead of us
ourselves in time but the future is
actually
the potentials that are implicated
in the present and he called these
potentials that they don't exist but
they
subsist and they play a part
in the causal emergence of the next
moment
we'll get back to this later when we at
the end of the last session we talk
about causality and a process approach
to causality
but the sense there's a lot more going
on than just the substance of what we
experience
so he said
consider the possibility space as an
infinite array
of dimensionless dots of
infinitesimally small but non-zero
capacity to connect with another dot
okay first i have to say he never said
this this
is a my metaphor
for getting into what he said okay so
the possibility space is an infinite ray
of dimensionless dots
they're they're they have no dimension
and they're infinitesimally small
but they have non-zero capacity to
connect with one another
so this is like pure subsisting
potential
right whitehead was a process relational
uh
philosopher so the array is
infinite so the potential is also
infinite
what actually exists is a small
fragment of what potentially exists
now we're going to look at this why this
is important later
because we're going to try to see an
alternative to complex adaptive systems
and move toward the concept of concept
potential states
so instead of always adapting reactively
to what exists
is to creatively potentiate what is
potential in this state so this move
from like
well what's out there is actually a
small fragment of what potentially
exists
because there's this infinite array of
potentiality and not all of it is
connected
the latent potential composes a
background
that is causally implicit
in what actually exists
so this is whitehead's way of
looking at this so if you look at
one galactic era ago
humans potentially existed then
and and in this reality
we subsisted then also and the future
potentially exists in the spaces
between these these connections that are
here today
so you start to compose a simultaneity
of potential in actuality
and this makes us feel more
intimate in in part of what is rather
than this
being suspended between the past and the
future and who are we and who are we
going to become like everything
everything is here to be sensed and to
be senseful with
right now it's all implicated and
anchored in
the actuality itself
so he's so potential subsist as
capacitors
can we learn not to react to adaptive
pressures
that word i'm going to throw out but can
instead we
sense into the potentials in the state
of the moment
new relationships are always threatening
to appear
just think how cool that feels
new relationships are always threatening
to appear we got a little hit of this
during kobit when some people are like
wow
things are moving now things are moving
now
and the sense of these we'll look at it
later also in terms of resilience
this sense of not being clinging that
all the connections that are already
here can't be
cut you know we don't want all the past
connections
and all the interget no we can we want
to disentangle some of the pieces so the
new potentials
that are threatening to appear this is
like a completely
different reframe with time and
potential
and of course this also resonates not
only with indigenous people
but with a lot of spiritual um mystical
um people and dogan said the time has
come
and beings appear
so this notion of
really if you think of like we started
off with does the world make sense well
this is a different reframe whether it
makes sense or not what is threatening
to appear
this is this is very this very
interesting
there's all these cracks now what's
threatening to appear it's
very vital very exciting i find it very
exciting
uh yeah so that's more of my orientation
to it
so where is where is time in this time
is
is is a simultaneity nothing has ever
you know i had this insight once nothing
is ever lost and nothing's ever gained
there's just this change between
potentials and actuals
and the movement between them
and it's it's it's less contracted than
this so it's civilization collapsing we
looked at this timeline i mean
is this little western civilization
collapsing
look look what had to happen for us to
get here
i mean taking a deep time even from a
modernity standpoint
perspective is can be very very limiting
but liberating
okay so this is another way
to look at it again which is to
we looked at it from whitehead's point
of view and
we're going to see the resonance with an
indigenous point of view so this notion
of
this is an indigenous painting again
it's very similar to this notion
of an infinite array of
capacitors do you see how that is very
similar
in this kind of
imagination or vision
of how reality comes to be
and so from this perspective
we could reimagine this notion of
appearances and disappearances
coming from the emerging and
disappearing from
and through the background potentials
as some things come into existence and
some things remain
subsistent or subsist in the background
and come come forth ground and be
background
nothing ever really lost nothing ever
really gained
you
in this this experience of where where
did those
beings go oh can you still see them in
there in the potential
for them to appear this would be
a kind of time freedom
so the takeaway here
is that we are weavers of time and we do
this freely
it just is the way our consciousness the
way conscious
human consciousness works but we have
been weaving
unconsciously and so we trap ourselves
in our own nets of knowing
so we want to become aware of our
weaving skills
and to be cognizant of what
what we weave is it working for us is it
limiting
us are there new ways to weave
these primary
structures of time
so this brings us back to where we
started we have the potential to be in
resonance with this time in between
worlds
instead of thinking as being suspended
in time
we see that something very unique is
emerged and we have
the potential to be in resonance to be
sense full
with this new feeling with these cracks
and holes in modernity
where things are threatening to appear
we could be eagerly await them
we could respond with openings and
welcomings
we have the potential to savor its
precious flavors
to articulate and communicate this as
dispatches to those
who are missing out of this time
instead of rushing to overcome it using
artifices of the one
that is falling away returning to the
background to the world of disappearance
that yes
modernity is falling away
returning to the background of
disappearance
that doesn't mean it's lost it means it
fully potentiates
the next moment it's causally implicated
in the next moment
this kind of change in our consciousness
would be of such
radical proportion
that if we were to gaze on the humans of
tomorrow
they would be barely recognizable
we would peer into the future and see
our future selves
the same way we peer at the animals
and see them as somehow other than us
and this is the existential anxiety
that we have by putting time
on a line we look into the past we don't
see ourselves in the animals they're
other than us
so here we are in between we look into
the future
we're afraid where will we go they're
other than
us so we're forever suspended
in between the life force that
is continuously in and simultaneous
in the deep past in the deep future
this notion of this this timeline this
this timeline thing makes us see the
stars as
other than us the animals is other than
us so here we are orphans
then when we see we might change ah this
is really sad the last of the mohicans
because what's coming through us
will also be other than us and so this
is incredible existential anxiety
that we don't see the our own continuity
it's this exact same move here into the
past
other than us appear into the future
other than us
what's left nothing we're we're in a
time between worlds where
we're temporary
short
so this is a kind of existential pickle
we put ourselves in with these
with these this this temporal frame of
modernity
and if you switch this around and you
look at nature and you look at the
animals
there i was i'm looking today
there i was it's a tremendous amount of
compassion
for not only how you resonate with them
but that whole long long long effort all
the things
that have been done have appeared
and disappeared in order to set the
conditions for you to be here
and that it's moving continually moving
toward
destinies that we share what we don't
know
contemplate instead that all spheres of
existence are coming into being together
in a time-space dimension that forms a
unity
in relationship
and i think this is the last slide so
we'll have plenty of time
for q and a
we are destined to be forever in between
never having completely left never
having
fully arrived
it has it has become the proposition of
our era to be
in a time between worlds
unable to reside among them
in resonance with their protect
perpetual fluxes
and flows
so there's a lot there
thank you bonita we'll jump into
questions now
just a reminder to everyone to post your
questions in the chat
and put a q or a question the word
question
in front so i can see it um
tanya if you are yeah there you are if
you'd like to ask your question go
for it
so benita once again just a fantastic
presentation thank you so very much
when you were speaking it reminded me of
some of the conceptions that i've come
across about
death i mean a lot of western society
fears death is not you know you prolong
life as long as you can and all this
kind of stuff
but i've also heard that
people don't actually really die
in in a real sense because
if they have touched others their
existence
lives in the other is this kind of
consistent with what you're talking
about yes um
it does lead to re trying to reinform us
about death
and there's a couple again i'm gonna
riff around but
it'll circle back um
so there's a couple of different ways to
look at this like
one of the thought experiments is to say
is the first amoeba
still around and you know how amoeba
reproduce they just
split into two and then like so is the
first amoeba still around
well yeah sort of right
um and that's more of what a process
view looks like
now because we don't see
we see we don't see the continuity
between
people because we see ourselves as
separate bodies
we don't it's harder for us to say is
the first
human still around
an amoeba you know it's not like you see
one of them go away
and we're hyper vigilant about well the
other one's not around
but if you could see the continuity like
you expressed
the person lives in the imagination in
the actions in the ripples
of their life those subsist
into the future
that's not comforting to an ego that's
contracted but that's a good start
another way to think about it is in
process philosophy
that number of potentials are infinite
and the number of actuals are infinite
but they're not exhaustive so there's
this notion of
so this is how whitehead talks and
that's why those quotes weren't
whiteheads but
what means to be infinite but not
exhaustive means
there are an infinite number of
potentials in the future
but some of them have been taken out of
existence
and i'll give you an example of what
kinds of things are taken
out of existence there was a time before
there were elephants
there may be a time when there are no no
more elephants
but there'll never be a time when there
were
no elephants and that always subsists
in the reality so the potential for
there never to have been elephants
that potentially is taken out of
existence
even though it's an infinite number of
potential so that's another way of look
at
the miracle and the preciousness of your
life
it's never taken out of existence
it never has a beginning i mean
you go back and then you think of the
first person and then a miracle happens
and then there's evolut you know
where do you start and you're never
taken out of existence
so from the from the here and now it's
like well what are you gonna do with
your life are you gonna
gonna worry about global trumpism
like i mean can you put that in
perspective you may
act on it but are you gonna worry about
it from a contracted space
you know so that's one another way to
look at it
and the third way to look at it is when
you're talking
deep evolution and you're talking about
the human species
so you might say um
there's a there's another way to look at
it because people today
uh another thought experiment is
okay i'm reconciled that i i'm going to
die
but i don't want humans to die and this
just
bumps up the problem at an
anthropocentric
uh level right so
it's like so that long timeline so
the the more if you can identify with
all the human race that's helpful but
then you don't want humans to go extinct
then if you can identify with life force
in general
and then you go on and on and on who are
you
identifying with what are you the
product of well you're a product of
all that that we saw and that doesn't go
away
um but that's that's
that's not salve you know it's not a
rough
it's not going to be satisfy the ego
but it is a background that you can be
aware of
and live from make your decisions from
that
uh from from more from that place
um
it's always tricky territory because it
doesn't mean well then forget i'm not
going to do anything
because you know the sun's going to die
out anyways
but what you do to address the suffering
or to speak to your neighbor is now
qualitatively different
because it's not driven by threat and
contraction
it's driven by a deep sense of
well-being belonging and intimacy
and humility because at a certain point
if you start to say well we have to take
control
like uh well then you have a god problem
because you say well i
i could design this thing better than
god
chances are you can't
um so all of that's in play in kind of
these thought experiments
um but death is certainly death and
extinction
are certainly two big ones um what goes
extinct
you know we'll look at a slide uh next
time these are all good questions
because they preview
are the dinosaurs extinct
well they just turned into birds it
depends where you
assign continuity and where you sign a
sign change
um if we ever manage to gmo not gmo but
to
to dinosaur dna
and then they come back did they go
extinct
extinction is not just the disappearance
and appearance of the dinosaurs
it's the change across time and the
potential
for them to be reanimated by science
let's say
so we spent too much time looking just
at the actual the substance
and not of all the potentials all the
protocols that are in the system
that can create new potentials
and that's something we can work on you
cannot work on the fact that you're
going to die
perhaps you can be you know you can be
uploaded into a computer and that
that makes some people happy but you
could also be
downloaded into your children or the
people you affect in your life
why doesn't that make people happy in
the same way
or you could be downloaded into
something that doesn't look like a human
a million years from now
um yeah
so that you know this these these
these sessions are meant to elicit just
that these kind of thought experiments
um
notice how many different ways you could
relate to time
and appearance and disappearance and how
few ways we do
and notice also how the indigenous
imagination
in the white head science which got
incorporated into a lot of modern signs
around quantum mechanics
are very resonant they're not these
aren't just throwback
kind of ideas
thank you bonita i think
skylar your question is a great
follow-up if you'd like to unmute
yourself and ask it
go for it hi bonnie
thank you so much um
yeah i just was feeling into
grief and um
you know thinking about the
that nothing ever is ever really lost
and nothing has ever really
gained what
why do we feel the loss so much or what
is the role of grief
maybe and and mourning um
in that case in the human experience
um yeah so this is very similar to what
came up last time so
we were talking about the affect streams
and how um there's a hand there's three
primary affects streams and there's
contracted forms
and there's ex or expanded forms and
then there's spiritual forms
and these are neuroanatomically and
neurochemically dynamically
identifiable in all mammalian bodies
so the affect stream of
connection is care
panic and grief so care is when you care
for something
someone a thing also
an animal or a thing what we call a
thing panic is the fear of
losing that
and grief is the experience of having
lost it
and so um
[Music]
when you so the move is to notice that
there's nothing wrong with grief it's
but it's the affect of
care the spiritual
hyper expanded or liberated form of that
is inter being or interconnectedness
or um
yeah this no feeling of being connected
with all things and all things being
connected so that the fear of losing or
having lost
goes away but
the way i relate to grief is um
and the way i relate to all affects is
first i i want to
have that awareness and understanding of
it
but you know affects come and go and
they take the time they take
and so if you notice you're in grief
that's okay
what's its function is an interesting
question
um it occurs to me i'm thinking as you
speak that
um it does show me what i care about
yeah it just is it's and the more you
grief you're just like wow i mean i
really
there was so much love there
that turns into another question you
know and of course
the the the act to
active move is to care more
and um not to care less
and and and liberate that energy of how
much
you cared and that you can care
and and yeah and this
sense of uh um someone just wrote it you
know
this one's taken out of existence it
liberates you to care
more care again care
for others and so to use that
decisive action is very important
um
that's different than this feeling and
this is important
some people have grief
i mean this happened to me these are all
things that i i
i have sharing you my experiences you'll
have grief
and then you look at it and you realize
the grief is much
seems out of proportion to the reality
so this is not really grief this is a
loss of connection with reality
it's not a loss of the thing you cared
for that's the trigger
and it feels like this it feels like you
walk around with a hole in your heart
it's just a hole and you realize you're
not really grieving over that person
you've discovered a hole in your heart
this can be there for many years you
just notice oh
here i am a successful woman i do this i
go to new york city every day
i have a hole in my heart that means you
you
don't you're not connected so it's not
the loss of that connection
it's just you you're just not connected
so be very
very careful to separate those two
things
some people when they lose they put all
their care into one individual
they agree for that individual yes but
the real thing is they realize
they want they're not connected to
anything else so there's a hole in their
heart
and that's a different problem does that
make sense
and literally the grief feels more like
in your heart this feels like right here
there's just a hole right there
here grief you hold mostly up here
panic up here
see and it moves to the lower chakras
because you're not connected
is that helpful amazing thank you
it's all right to have a hole in your
heart uh when it happened to me i did
nothing about it i just
just knew i had a hole in my heart
so we've got a few questions here
and they're very similar it almost
doesn't matter
who asks their question and they're
about
um how do we embody
this new relationship with potentiality
um and so yeah maybe keep that in mind
bonita that this is touched on in
a few different questions but i'll let
victor if you're here
he'd like to ask your question hey
hi bonnie uh so my question came out as
what do you feel it means to be in right
relationship to potentialities
right um i really liked what pradeep
said too so i'll read his as well
so what he said was like what heuristics
do you consider in choosing
to actualize across an infinite
potentialities
um is it based on well-being compassion
um you know that's kind of some of the
same flavor but yeah that's
yeah it's you know it's funny because i
see
a lot of this work right now as um
metacognitive um
and so so um i'll start with there and
then i'll work to maybe
more of what you asked in your question
so and for me it's kind of like we'll
get to this i'm glad we're asking this
now because we're going to be crunched
for time
and we're going to end up time changing
causality
and we're going to end up seeing that
almost
all of what we think of causality
comes in the insist with systems now is
complex adaptive processes
it took me a long time because i kept on
thinking about systems and
find out that i couldn't think of them
outside of this
and what happens is at first we
imagined complex adaptation as the agent
in the environment the environment
exerts pressure
and the organisms adapt and that's not
really what darwinian
darwin said but i call it the darwinian
attitude we we
take it like that then we get to this
funny place where we say no the
environment's adapting too
right so that's a good move uh
but then what happens is we get to the
anthropocene
where the environment is actually being
uh
really put a lot of pressure on by
humans now we have a closed loop
in our in our model of change everything
is adapting to everything else
and it'll just it'll just it's like a
perpetual arms race
every and it's just it's just it's just
the news is tightening
and this is how we think about climate
this is how we think about the markets
this is how we think about everything
so this is self-destructive conceptual
uh material so the first thing is
is to really
work hard at not thinking of things that
way
in the first and the first way you do
that
is you notice the absurdity of it
it's like uh antibiotics
and uh and bacteria
and insects and pesticides and and
markets and the speed of trade and
nuclear warheads and nuclear defense and
everything is like this right
but what's really hard is then to ask
yourself well what is going on
and it's almost impossible at first to
see
something else going on do i feel
pressure from the economy yeah but then
i say but
that i don't want to see that so a lot
of it
really has to do in my experience with
working hard
at metacognitively releasing
that um that kind of way of looking at
systems and so
um i started doing that a lot for
a while and then um in
2012 i had the
opportunity to lose my career of 33
years
and you know i was really good at what i
was doing we just bought the farm
everything was like you know generative
and adapting
and i would wake up in the morning and i
would look into the future and i'd see
nothing there was nothing to adapt to
there was like everything was just
done over and my husband's in the
contracting industry also
the housing bubble burst and little by
little
my relationship to
that changed you know when you're in
business you're always under threat and
you're adapting and this and then you're
strategizing
so then i started talking about complex
potential states
and complex potential states theory
which um initially and we'll get into it
more conceptually but initially uh took
the form of this
um okay so
here i have a plant and then here i have
insects on my plants
hmm what's the potential in this like
what is it about
this situation there's more life here
now
okay so you want to feel like oh there's
less life well
now i have insects on my plants there's
more life here now
what's the potential in that little by
little
you you do these things with your mind
but it opens your organs of perception
and you start to see ah
i have those bluebirds now and all of a
sudden
the way things unfold is different than
they did before
because your actions on them have
changed because your questions changed
so i know that this is truly
something to experiment around with but
it's very subtle but the first part is
just noticing how
you have to commit to i'm just not going
to see
just not going to look at things from
the darwinian attitude
and at first there's nothing to put in
its place
um and and that's a really funny thing
to place to be in because
because of the way we'll see this next
time because the more people that
believe in the darwinian attitude
the more society acts as if that's
actually happening which
projects back onto you reason to believe
that that's what's actually happening
so you get this feedback loop right uh
if if i think
china is going if if i'm afraid china is
gonna
invade us then we get ready to be
invaded china sees that
so then they invade us so having the
darwinian attitude is actually creates
real ontology real darwinian dynamics
so it gets difficult to
pull out of that but i think that
um for me that that's that's how the
process
runs
so that would be the embodied thing
first metacognitively and then
just try not to
to use that framing not having any other
frame
that changes your behaviors that changes
what's actual
and then you see oh my god a change in
my frame or suspension of that actually
changes something
it's a it's an interesting way to live
thanks bonita i think that's a good um
good segue into this question from tim
there's a couple questions around
um intention and agency and they seem
related
and and tim's question if you'd like to
ask it
about agency and defeatism kind of ties
into some of the like adaptive fear that
you were talking about
sure sure um i'll just
i'll ask the question as i phrase it and
then i can clarify if needed but i said
um could you speak to the paradox of
agency
a little bit with regard to the fear of
stepping into futures that are unknown
um seems to me like there's a lot of
folks in the world of complexity that i
hear and i may be
mishearing or mischaracterizing who
seem to become almost defeatist about
human consciousness like it's almost
sort of the
not in a religious sense but like the
original sin right like that our
consciousness
is um really problematic and so then
what that seems to translate into is
like
um we we can't make decisions that
uh that our agency is actually a a
negative
thing and so i'm wondering if you could
speak to that a little bit because it
kind of
to me is like the abyss of all abysses
yeah yeah so for example
um the original sin of being human
right this is like very buddhist
and christian and um
uh it's it's in the
anthropocene imagination right so
um i'm gonna
i'm gonna get right to your answer but
i'm going to
talk around it so for example um
the people who think
the environmentalists always have had
this problem
because on the one hand when they're
feeling good
they'll argue that well people are
nature you know people are natural we
should have natural we have natural
needs
we need to live in natural environments
we're just nature
but then they'll say well people are
destroying nature so basically you've
said nature is destroying itself and
now do you think nature is evil or is
nature
you know 100 good and so you get into
this tautology so
um the agency
so if you believe in the continuity of
life the agency of people
is the age agency of life is the agency
of nature
but it's also a long game right so
there's
there's there's um
you can't um define the whole from
these short this short time
of modernity so that's that's one thing
another thing is um whenever we talk
about
agency there's two types of agency one
type of meanings in that one type is
the ability to act out or behave on my
own
intentions right so
can i speak my truth that's agency
now the ability to predict what effect
that has
is different than agency right so is my
agency coupled with predictable outcomes
no um
but one of the reasons why that disturbs
us
is again and we're going to look at this
and when we look at causality
is because basically we think agency
in order for it to have
outcomes it has to act like the billiard
ball
uh notion of causality that my agency
has to trigger something that then
triggers something that then triggers
something and down that linear path is
the outcome i want and that's not
how complex systems work um
if i take a billiard ball it's called
the billiard ball
theory of causality you know one billion
ball hits another and
hits another and hits another and we
sometimes think that human agency should
be like that and when we find out it's
not like that
we say we either we don't have any
agency well we have
agency because not all people have
agency but if you can
act on your own intentions and your own
motivation you have agency
but you're not a billiard ball that then
hits another billiard ball accurately
and down the line you get what you want
and
if you think of this the difference
between if i
have a billiard ball and i hit another
billiard ball
we think of that as you know we do the
physics
in terms of angles and linear angles and
stuff like that
it works for a billiard balls but what's
really happening
is if i take a billiard ball and throw
it in the pond
what happens ripples right
well when a billiard ball hits another
billiard ball the same thing is
happening
energy is rippling but the
but the ripple effect is inconsequential
to
the scale at which we want the movement
to happen so we don't include it
does that make sense this is a metaphor
i'm going fast but
so the same thing with our agency
agencies just
it's like throwing you throw yourself in
the pond and then there's ripple effects
you don't have control over those so you
can't
linearly tie yourself into projected
outcomes like a billiard ball but when
you ask that question of agency and then
you get nervous that's what you're doing
i can have agency if i can't do the
physics the linear physics from
here to my outcome
so again it's a matter of taking the
mental models in which we ask our
question to be very very careful
that one mental model is not create
that's where a paradox come from because
we're in one mental model that doesn't
make sense with the other mental model
and we try to put them together and
and the question self-destructs into a
paradox
we'll look at that more um in the in the
uh
causality the last one
which is where all these time change and
then we get to causality
which is where we're going
uh yeah so potential is like into a
capacitor which discharges the capacitor
so
that's a very interesting thought
experiment
where i go with that when you when you
look at
causality if you get outside of the the
billiard ball
model of causality which even when you
throw the billiard ball into the water
that metaphor has has some of that in it
at the bottom you you end up
um with a lot of the pan psychists and
neo-animists
and that is that um
that the capacitors are self-animated
and um this is actually a move that's
happening in the amount that happened in
the imagination of einstein for example
he said there's no such thing as gravity
there's not like the earth
and then in gravity mass
itself self animate space
which we call gravity it it has the
property
that curve space it's self animating you
don't need gravity
to add to the earth to curve space
right so um
the same thing like when i was a kid
and we learned like you know you take an
iron bar
i think a magnet and
you wrap copper around it and then
it electricity flows through it right
and you would i would say well where
does electricity come from and this
the teacher would say no you just take
the magnet and you wrap copper around it
and you get electricity so we tend to
have this this mental model
of force and
objects this newtonian and objects have
no
power or agency unless a force acts on
it
right this is so what gives the
what gives the capacitors the potential
to connect nothing
they have self potential
you start to realize that this right
reframe itself is very powerful
what does gives you what gives the
electricity is not something
plus the magnets
and the copper wire
it's what they do when they're in
relationship
so you can say well where does
electricity come from
so the way we we relate to this word
force is like it's
something other than the bodies in
relationship
and this is what the way we relate to
our life force we think that
our life force is in our body the way a
glove is in a hand
but there is the potential that all the
bodies in my body including my cells
there's many
scales of bodies and the molecules in my
cells
and the atoms in my molecules they all
have
self and they're all self animating
in their own characteristic and then you
put bodies in relationship to each other
and you have new potentials and that's
actually part of my
theory of complex potential states
bodies in relationship
constitute potential so the capacitors
you know they're self potentiating to
connect
and then when they connect when they're
in relationship even in proximity
they're self animated to connect so
that's how the theory goes
um um you can take it as a you know
a theory constitutive metaphor um
but uh that would be uh
other people have written sort of like
this is graham harmon and neoanimism
and again it's white hedian um basically
essentially white hedian
and process philosophy and some of the
uh
the the the buddhists and the chan
buddhists
so let me just follow up on that a
little bit so if the
interaction with the terrain around here
the people around you
is part of what creates the potential
where does agency come into play
so this helped the animator has some
agency too right
exactly well that's interesting because
you know
even um this is a funny thing because
it's disembodied so i don't want to go
there but like
e when you just have you put a boy next
to a frog
and they both have their own agency but
then something there's a
there's something else that's being
composed like boys like the poke frogs
or
uh it doesn't even have to be a frog uh
this is very weird but like john paul
sartre in what's that long book he wrote
the big big one not being in time but
something like
anyways he even said that a hole in the
ground
animates a boy so like even even certain
features of the world you know like you
want to put your hand in it right
um so um so when i talk about bodies in
space i just mean any
any kind of proximity and um
um i talk about how
coffee every morning coffee animates
millions of people this is neoanimism so
if you really look at it who's moving
who
you know is the coffee moving me
um you know the the shamans are like
this they move through the forest and
then the plant calls them they can smell
that's what they need that has some
well-being so
um the agency
is another term for its your own
self-animation
right it's very close to it um
yeah it's interesting because we'll talk
about
how um philosophically people
got into like there's a
like if i have an intention to move my
arm
how does the intention this was
descartes problem how does not
substantive intention move my arm
and that's like well the agency is the
intention
and then somehow it has to make an arm
move but again this is the billiard ball
uh notion of causation that the
intention has to trigger the arm
and that there's a gap and so
the the intention and the arm arise
simultaneously
or or you have to you have to move to
different
different ways of speaking about this
and because we all know it's silly
to use a billiard ball model of
causality
to talk about these complex things but
it's very hard for us to get outside of
them
and you'll find that even in some of
these sophisticated maneuvers and
complexity science
ultimately that's the framework they're
working on
and and it hasn't really escaped that
reductive newtonian
um newtonian thing um in my paper
what will i say ultimately you have to
learn how to become the first mover
you're not reacting to something you
don't know where you're going
but you just have to do something and
and the truth is
that happens anyways you're going to get
up tomorrow and breathe
so can you put take that energy and put
it
put it somewhere new it's very hard to
do something new or
out of nothing but it's possible
well given how your environment sort of
gives
you a range of possibilities i'm not
sure
about that i once was in an office where
uh we were working for henry kissinger
and
we took care of his um um property here
in connecticut and they were having a
state
department you know nancy was having
this state department dinner there or
something and
um we had really really cold spring and
a cold rain and it killed her pop uh
yeah her poppies not her puppies her
her what are those called can't remember
um and she had like a mile drive of them
and um um
she was hysterical she wanted them
replaced by the next day because
it was ugly and they were like 40 year
old
uh plants and it was impossible and
people are running around like
trying to adapt to this crisis right
which was impossible and i'm like watch
this office like get everybody on the
phone
and it was like crazy so like i didn't
want to add to like the yet i was ahead
of operations i didn't want to add
to yet another voice just yelling at
people so
i stood on my head in the middle of the
office and waited for someone to notice
and then we reframed the problem so
so it can be very playful
and then when they noticed i said you're
talking about a person who
systematically
watched her husband systematically
and you know kill innocent people in
lebanon i think she'll get over this or
something like that
uh yeah she used to uh she used to
complain that some of
the workers the maintenance people that
we sent to our house were hats
you know these garden heads and she
refused
she didn't she wouldn't have that
because it reminded her of
vietnamese people she was crazy
okay uh
that was a that was a uh what divergence
but something like that trying to bring
out like
that's what you have to that's what
comes up when you
start thinking of just being a first
mover it becomes very playful
and crazy and uh it's a difference that
can make a difference but you don't know
what direction
it's going to go
maybe one more question
yeah um i've got a good question
from robert stonehill if you'd like to
unmute yourself
um hi you first um
as like practical takeaways uh the first
thing that individuals can do
is work on metacognition uh for
non-reactivity and
the second thing that uh
you've talked a lot about imagination
and it seems like a lot of these ideas
require
a vivid or a deep imagination
um what are ways that we can develop
this imagination thanks
yeah so everybody has
imagination all the time right because
all these all these common ways we think
about time
are actually imaginaries so
so we are we are built to serve up
imagination um the way we get
caught up in the war on sense making
there's a war
that's an imaginary okay it's a
meaningful fiction
so first to notice that no one's not
unpossessed of imaginaries
that this is always happening
so the first step is to notice
how much of this is imaginary
and then being able to okay i'm going to
do a jordan peterson
clean your room is this an imaginary you
want
being served up automatically without
your choice
or not and if it's not just get rid of
it now in the meantime you have nothing
nothing it's for for a while maybe
nothing interesting happens
but something will because you can't
help but be an imaginary add imagination
to your experience because you're a
human being
now you could sit on the cushion and get
rid of that entirely
but that's not useful because you won't
you won't be imaginary
and the people that do that very well
they add imagination to it
too the animations add imagination like
emptiness
or awareness rising from storehouse
consciousness those are imaginaries too
as far as i'm concerned unless you're
into
completely non-conceptual non-conscious
awareness
something's going to be served up in
your imagination
so first be aware of all of that that's
the metacognitive skill
and then try to clean your room
nature abhors a vacuum the mind of
uh not having something in there that's
imagination
um yeah so um
playfulness stubbornness is like ah
i just don't want to think that way like
i'm tired of it like
it's just boring it's boring do you
wanna do i wanna live my whole life
like like worried about that
no i mean it becomes easier when you get
old because there's only so many years
left and you're like really no
you know so you become stubborn or
committed to
like
yeah sometimes living in something
that's so completely imaginary you don't
even believe it is helpful too
as long as you know you're living
through that imaginary you know children
pretend all the time
they have wild pretends and you read
some of these
vygotsky transcripts of children can
pretend
and let's say there's only two children
so one's pretending to the father the
other one but then
this one has to be the grandmother of
that father and they have all these
levels
but they know they're pretending you
know they're wildly imaginative
and and this apparently is is very is
required to learn
learn something new
good questions i don't think that's a
full answer but
um it's a good question um
okay i think we did good we had nice 45
minutes of question and answers
this time so that was a little better in
terms of participation
yeah thank you so much bonita that was
great
um i'm gonna plug a couple events uh
we've got um collective presencing
um which is next in half an hour
and um if you're enjoying
the work with bonita maybe you can say
something about this bonita
high pitch conversations in a new key
um your cheekily named event um anything
you want to say about that bonita
coming up on october 25th uh yeah
so it's an experiment being run by a
group
of women i don't know if skyler is still
on this call
but myself skyler brown rio beck
nora batesome and miriam mason martino
and eche anderson
i don't know how to say her last name um
it's
um um
it's called conversat it's called high
pitch conversations and a new key
because we're trying to bring something
to
the podcast space um that's different
and that uh is absent and that
may be something people are looking for
other than that we don't know much about
it ourselves
or kind of scared uh but
um the chance to be with a group of
uh women who are all exceptional very
different
um and don't know what they're doing
together
except they want to do this together
how's that
look awesome
thank you thanks everyone um here's the
links to the slides again if you're
interested
thank you so much bonita for your time
and for your
obvious uh effort that you've put into
these presentations
see you all next week
chasing the rainbow
a dream so far away